<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ember | darthdeus' blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://darthdeus.github.io/blog/categories/ember/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://darthdeus.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-04T15:49:32+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://darthdeus.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jakub Arnold]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[State Manager and Friends - part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://darthdeus.github.io/blog/2013/01/27/state-manager-and-friends/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-27T19:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://darthdeus.github.io/blog/2013/01/27/state-manager-and-friends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since state management is such a huge part of Ember.js it desrves a
dedicated article. I'm not going to explain the old router which used
<code>Ember.StateManager</code> to do it's bidding. Those days are over and we
should all be moving towards the v2 router (or v2.2 so to speak).
Instead we're going to go deep into the <code>Ember.StateManager</code>.</p>

<p>In the general concept, state manager is basically some object which
manages states and the transitions between them, thus representing a
finite state machine.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><meta http-equiv="refresh" content="0; url=http://blog.trackets.com/2013/01/27/state-manager-and-friends.html">
<link rel="canonical" href="http://blog.trackets.com/2013/01/27/state-manager-and-friends.html" /></p>

<p>Let's say we have a <code>Post</code> which can be in two states, <code>draft</code> and
<code>published</code>. It begins it's life as a <code>draft</code> and when we <code>publish</code> it,
it should send out a notification email. The way Ember would handle this
is that it would assign a <code>Ember.StateManager</code> instance to the <code>Post</code>
instance and have that manage it's state (that's not exactly true in
Ember Data, but we'll get into that).</p>

<p>For now let's just say that this is the code we have</p>

<p>```javascript
PostManager = Ember.StateManager.extend({
  states: {</p>

<pre><code>draft: Ember.State.create(),
published: Ember.State.create()
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});</p>

<p>Post = Ember.Object.extend({
  title: null,
  init: function() {</p>

<pre><code>this.set("stateManager", PostManager.create());
this._super();
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>This gives us a really basic implementation. I'm setting the
<code>stateManager</code> property in the <code>init</code> function to avoid sharing the
instance across multiple <code>Post</code> instances. I'll explain this in a
followup article, for now just remember that if you need to set a
property to an object instance, you have to do that in the <code>init</code>
function, not directly like <code>stateManager: PostManager.create()</code>.</p>

<p>OK, we are now ready to list all of the states a <code>Post</code> can have.</p>

<p>```javascript
post = Post.create();
post.get("stateManager.states"); // => { draft: ..., published: ... }</p>

<p>post.get("stateManager.currentState"); // => null
```</p>

<p>We forgot to say which of the states should be the default. Let's
do that.</p>

<p>```javascript
PostManager = Ember.StateManager.extend({
  initialState: "draft",
  states: {</p>

<pre><code>draft: Ember.State.create(),
published: Ember.State.create()
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>From now every single post we create will be a <code>draft</code></p>

<p><code>javascript
post = Post.create();
post.get("stateManager.currentState.name"); // =&gt; "draft"
</code></p>

<p>And we can also make it transition into another state</p>

<p><code>javascript
post = Post.create();
post.get("stateManager").transitionTo("published");
post.get("stateManager.currentState.name"); // =&gt; "published"
</code></p>

<p>But <code>Ember.StateManager</code> can do more than that. We can hook into both
<code>enter</code> and <code>exit</code> events on each state and do some magic! Let's
redefine our state manager as this</p>

<p>```javascript
PostManager = Ember.StateManager.extend({
  initialState: "draft",
  states: {</p>

<pre><code>draft: Ember.State.create(),
published: Ember.State.create({
  enter: function() {
    console.log("post was published");
  }
})
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});</p>

<p>post = Post.create();
post.get("stateManager").transitionTo("published");
// console prints "post was published"
```</p>

<p>Understanding how this class works is essential for any Ember developer,
as it is being used in almost every part of the framework. We'll take at
some specific examples in the second part of this artcile.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ember Data in Depth]]></title>
    <link href="http://darthdeus.github.io/blog/2013/01/27/ember-data-in-depth/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-27T13:52:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://darthdeus.github.io/blog/2013/01/27/ember-data-in-depth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a guide explaining how Ember Data works internaly. My initial
motivation for writing this is to understand Ember better myself. I've
found that every time I understand something about how Ember works, it
improves my application code.</p>

<h2>Main parts</h2>

<p>First we need to understand what are the main concepts. Let's start with
a simple example.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><meta http-equiv="refresh" content="0; url=http://blog.trackets.com/2013/01/27/ember-data-in-depth.html">
<link rel="canonical" href="http://blog.trackets.com/2013/01/27/ember-data-in-depth.html" /></p>

<p><code>javascript
App.User = DS.Model.extend({
  username: DS.attr("string")
});
</code></p>

<p>Let's dive deep into this. There are four important concepts, two of
which are basic Ember.js and we're going to skip them</p>

<ul>
<li><code>App.User</code> represents a <code>User</code> class in the <code>App</code> namespace</li>
<li><code>username</code> represents a property on the <code>User</code> class</li>
</ul>


<p>These are the basics and you should be familiar with them to understand
the rest of this guide. Next we have <code>DS.Model</code> and <code>DS.attr</code>:</p>

<h2>DS.Model and DS.attr</h2>

<p><code>DS.Model</code> is one of the core concepts in Ember Data and it represents a
single <em>resource</em>. Models can have relationships with other models,
similar to how you'd model your data in a relational database. But let's
ignore that for now.</p>

<p><code>DS.Model</code> is both a state machine and a promise. If you don't
understand what promises are, please take a look at <a href="https://gist.github.com/3889970">this awesome
article</a> which explains them in depth.</p>

<p>State machines are used throughout Ember and they basically represent something <em>which can have multiple states and can transition between the states</em>. For example <code>DS.Model</code> can have the following states (<em><a href="http://emberjs.com/guides/models/model-lifecycle/">taken from the official Ember guide</a></em>):</p>

<ul>
<li><code>isLoaded</code> - The adapter has finished retrieving the current state of the record from its backend.</li>
<li><code>isDirty</code> - The record has local changes that have not yet been saved by the adapter. This includes records that have been created (but not yet saved) or deleted.</li>
<li><code>isSaving</code> - The record has been sent to the adapter to have its changes saved to the backend, but the adapter has not yet confirmed that the changes were successful.</li>
<li><code>isDeleted</code> - The record was marked for deletion. When <code>isDeleted</code> is true and <code>isDirty</code> is <code>true</code>, the record is deleted locally but the deletion was not yet persisted. When <code>isSaving</code> is true, the change is in-flight. When both <code>isDirty</code> and <code>isSaving</code> are <code>false</code>, the change has been saved.</li>
<li><code>isError</code> - The adapter reported that it was unable to save local changes to the backend. This may also result in the record having its <code>isValid</code> property become false if the adapter reported that server-side validations failed.</li>
<li><code>isNew</code> - The record was created locally and the adapter did not yet report that it was successfully saved.
<code>isValid</code> No client-side validations have failed and the adapter did not report any server-side validation failures.</li>
</ul>


<p>We can also bind to these with event handlers, which will be explained later, but for now let's just list them:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>didLoad</code></li>
<li><code>didCreate</code></li>
<li><code>didUpdate</code></li>
<li><code>didDelete</code></li>
<li><code>becameError</code></li>
<li><code>becameInvalid</code></li>
</ul>


<p><em><a href="https://github.com/emberjs/data/blob/f274153754cb8b629cd98fc6c590f18bc8ee3ff6/packages/ember-data/lib/system/model/states.js#L223-L245">I would also encourage you to go take a look at the source documentation on GitHub</a></em></p>

<p>It is important for us to understand what each state means, because they
can affect how our application behaves. For example if we try to modify
a record which is already being saved, we will get an exception saying
something like this</p>

<p><code>
Attempted to handle event `willSetProperty` on &lt;App.User:ember1144:null&gt;
while in state rootState.loaded.created.inFlight. Called with
{reference: [object Object], store: &lt;App.Store:ember313&gt;, name: username}
</code></p>

<p>The important part here is the <code>rootState.loaded.created.inFlight</code>. If
we look at <a href="https://github.com/emberjs/data/blob/f274153754cb8b629cd98fc6c590f18bc8ee3ff6/packages/ember-data/lib/system/model/states.js#L254-L261">the source of <code>DirtyState</code></a>, we can see what this means</p>

<blockquote><p>Dirty states have three child states:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>uncommitted</code>: the store has not yet handed off the record to be saved.</li>
<li><code>inFlight</code>: the store has handed off the record to be saved, but the adapter has not yet acknowledged success.</li>
<li><code>invalid</code>: the record has invalid information and cannot be send to the adapter yet.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Let's go through the record lifecycle and observe it's state. We can do
this by doing <code>.get("stateManager.currentState.name")</code></p>

<p>```javascript
user = App.User.find(1)
user.get("isLoaded") // => true
user.get("isDirty") // => false
user.get("stateManager.currentState.name") // => loaded</p>

<p>user.set("username", "wycats")
user.get("isLoaded") // => true
user.get("isDirty") // => true, which means comitting the transaction will save the record
user.get("stateManager.currentState.name") // => uncommitted</p>

<p>user.get("transaction").commit()
// while the record is being saved
user.get("stateManager.currentState.name") // => inFlight
user.get("isSaving") // => true
// after the record was saved
user.get("stateManager.currentState.name") // => saved
```</p>

<h2>Transactions and <code>commit()</code></h2>

<p>In the previous example, we've used <code>get("transaction").commit()</code> to
persist the changes to the server. <code>.commit()</code> will take all <code>dirty</code>
records in the transaction and persiste them to the server.</p>

<p>A record becomes dirty whenever one of it's attributes change. For
example</p>

<p><code>javascript
user = App.User.find(1)
user.get("isDirty") // =&gt; false
user.set("username", "wycats")
user.get("isDirty") // =&gt; true
</code></p>

<p>If we create a new record, it will be dirty by default</p>

<p><code>javascript
user = App.User.createRecord()
user.get("isDirty") // =&gt; true
</code></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/emberjs/data/pull/646">Currently there's a regression</a>
that we change an attribute to something else, and then back to the
original value, the record will be marked as dirty.</p>

<p>```javascript
user = App.User.find(1)
originalUsername = user.get("username")</p>

<p>user.get("isDirty") // => false
user.set("username", "wycats")
user.get("isDirty") // => true
user.set("username", originalUsername)
user.get("isDirty") // => true, even though it should be false
```</p>

<p>But let's hope this will be fixed soon.</p>

<h2>Transactions</h2>

<p>Until now we assumed that there is some <em>global</em> transaction which is
the same for every single model. But this doesn't have to be true. We
can create our own transactions and manage them at our will.</p>

<p>I recommend you take a look at <a href="https://github.com/emberjs/data/blob/master/packages/ember-data/tests/integration/transactions/basic_test.js">the tests for transactions in Ember Data
repository</a>.
They basically show all of the scenarios which you can encounter. For
example</p>

<p>```javascript
transaction = store.transaction();
record = transaction.createRecord(App.User, {});</p>

<p>transaction.commit(); // this will save the record to the server</p>

<p>record.set("foo", "bar");
transaction.commit(); // nothing is committed here, because the record</p>

<pre><code>                  // is removed from the transaction when it is saved
</code></pre>

<p>store.commit(); // this will save the record properly
```</p>

<p>We can also add a record to a transaction, which will remove it from the
global transaction. Important thing to note here is that
<a href="https://github.com/emberjs/data/blob/master/packages/ember-data/lib/system/store.js#L127-L129"><code>store.transaction()</code></a>
<strong>always returns a new transaction</strong>.</p>

<p>```javascript
user = App.User.find(1);
transaction = store.transaction();
transaction.add(user);</p>

<p>user.set("username", "wycats");</p>

<p>store.commit(); // nothing happens
transaction.commit(); // user is saved
```</p>

<p>Same goes for deleting records</p>

<p>```javascript
user = App.User.find(1);
transaction = store.transaction();
transaction.add(user);</p>

<p>user.deleteRecord();</p>

<p>store.commit(); // nothing happens
transaction.commit(); // user is deleted
```</p>

<p>We can also remove a record from a transaction</p>

<p>```javascript
user = App.User.find(1);
transaction = store.transaction();</p>

<p>transaction.add(user);
transaction.remove(user);</p>

<p>user.set("name", "wycats");</p>

<p>transaction.commit(); // nothing happens
```</p>

<p>One scenario when transactions can be useful is when you just need to
change one record, without affecting changes to other records. You can
put that change in a separate transaction, instead of just doing
<code>store.commit()</code>.</p>

<p>Important thing to note here is that there's a <code>defaultTransaction</code> for
the store to which you can get via <code>store.get("defaultTransaction")</code>.
This is where all of the records are placed, unless you explicitly
create a new transaction and assign a record to it.</p>

<p>These two are completely equivalent</p>

<p><code>javascript
store.commit();
store.get("defaultTransaction").commit();
</code></p>

<p>Just take a look at how <code>store.commit()</code> is defined</p>

<p><code>javascript
commit: function() {
  get(this, 'defaultTransaction').commit();
},
</code></p>

<h2><code>commit()</code></h2>

<p>Now that we understand how transactions work, let's dig deep into
<code>store.commit()</code>. First thing we need to understand here is that Ember
Transactions use this thing called <code>bucket</code> to store records with
various states in. This is first initialized in the <a href="https://github.com/emberjs/data/blob/master/packages/ember-data/lib/system/transaction.js#L91-L101"><code>init</code> method of
<code>DS.Transaction</code></a></p>

<p>```javascript
init: function() {
  set(this, 'buckets', {</p>

<pre><code>clean:    Ember.OrderedSet.create(),
created:  Ember.OrderedSet.create(),
updated:  Ember.OrderedSet.create(),
deleted:  Ember.OrderedSet.create(),
inflight: Ember.OrderedSet.create()
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  set(this, 'relationships', Ember.OrderedSet.create());
}
```</p>

<p>Each bucket represents one state in which a record can possibly be.
These are used in many different places in the transaction, and every
time a method changes it's state, it will be moved to a corresponding
bucket</p>

<p><code>javascript Example of recordBecameDirty
recordBecameDirty: function(bucketType, record) {
  this.removeFromBucket('clean', record);
  this.addToBucket(bucketType, record);
},
</code></p>

<p><strong>More content will be coming soon</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
